Finding aid to the Lawrence Lader papers SSC.MS.00704
Sophia Smith Collection
Lawrence Lader papers
1929-2005
Sophia Smith Collection
Lader, Lawrence
SSC.MS.00704
12.5 linear feet (14 boxes )
Lawrence Lader (1919-2006) was a birth control and abortion-rights activist and author. Among many other actions, he co-founded NARAL Pro-Choice America with Betty Friedan and others, and was active in the lawsuits that made RU-486 legal in the United States in 2000. This collection documents his work as an author and activist for women's reproductive rights, including safe and legal abortion.
Conditions Governing Access
The first series in this collection, consisting of the materials donated in 2012, is closed until processed per the deed of gift. The 2018 additions to the collection are open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The first portion of the Lawrence Lader Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by his widow Joan Lader in 2012 (accession 12S-71). Later additions were sent by his colleague, Marshall Beil, who was asked by Joan Lader to review the materials before donation (accessions 2018-S-0006 and 2018-S-0013).
Biographical Note
Lawrence Lader (1919-2006) was a birth control and abortion-rights activist and author. Among many other actions, he co-founded NARAL Pro-Choice America with Betty Friedan and others, and was active in the lawsuits that made RU-486 legal in the United States in 2000.
Lawrence Powell Lader was born in Manhattan in 1919; his father was a successful business man whose family owned a food additive company. In 1941 he graduated from Harvard University; while a student there, he co-founded the first student-run radio station as well as worked on the university's newspaper, The Crimson. Before joining the Army in 1942, Lader spent one year as the program director for the Intercollegiate Broadcasting System, an ABC affiliate. While in the Army (1942-1946), he rose from private to lieutenant and served mostly in the South Pacific and as chief, Troop Information, New York office, Armed Forces Radio. After WWII, Lader began writing for several of the nation's leading publications, publishing hundreds of articles over the next six decades. His work appeared in, among others, The Nation, New Yorker, Look, and the New York Times.
In 1955, Lader published the first of his twelve books, The Margaret Sanger Story. He would later say that he "admired her fiery commitment and said she undoubtedly was the greatest influence on my life"(LA Times, 5/14/06). Lader would devote most of the rest of his life to making birth control accessible and abortion safe and legal. In 1969, he and others, including long-time friend Betty Friedan, founded the National Association for the Repeal of Abortion Laws, now known as NARAL Pro-Choice America. By 1976, Lader felt that NARAL was not acting aggressively enough and founded his own organization, Abortion Rights Mobilization (ARM) which was especially active in the 1980s, fighting the power of the Catholic Church and in the 1990s, working to make RU-486, the banned abortion pill, available in the US. That goal was achieved in 2000 when the US Food and Drug Administration finally approved the drug, marked under the name of Mifeprex.
The titles of Laders several books reflect his life work and include, in addition to the Sanger biography, Abortion (1966) and Abortion II: Making the Revolution (1973), Politics, Power, and the Church: the Catholic Crisis and the Challenge to American Pluralism (1987), and RU 486: The Pill That Could End the Abortion Wars and Why American Women Dont Have It (1991). Earlier in his career, he wrote about race in New Yorks Bloodiest Week: The Draft Riots of 1863 Turned a Great City into a Living Hell (1959) and The Bold Brahmins: New Englands War Against Slavery, 1831-1863 (1961). Politically, Lawrence Lader was very much on the extreme left--as a young man, he was district leader for Repreresentative Vito Marcantonio,"still considered one of the country's most radical congressmen."(NYT, 5/10/06) At the age of twenty-nine, Lader ran unsuccessfully for the New York State Assembly on Marcantonios American Labor Party ticket. His first marriage (1942-1946) was to Jean MacInnis who was just as progressive. While married to Lader, she kept her own name and a separate bank account.
In 1961, Lader married Joan Summers with whom he had a daughter, Wendy Summers Lader. Lader died of colon cancer at the age of 86. After he died in 2006, his wife of forty-five years told the Los Angeles Times that Lader "kept pressing the cause of abortion rights until his death...one of [his] last acts was to pay for an ad in a Sioux Falls newspaper" in protest over South Dakota's 2006 law banning abortions.
Scope and Contents
The Lawrence Lader papers document his work as an author and activist for women's reproductive rights, including safe and legal abortion.
The first accession of materials, from 2012, includes articles, manuscripts, published books, correspondence, notebooks, publicity, and radio scripts. Especially well-documented is Lader's effort in the 1990s to make RU 486 available in the US. The papers include examples of Lader's school work from grade school through college, as well as multiple drafts of an unpublished memoir, but otherwise do not include many records of a personal nature.
The additions to the records received in 2018 contain records relating to three significant lawsuits in which Lader was involved: Baker v Abortion Rights Mobilization (ARM), relating to the enforcement of the anti-electioneering provisions of IRS Code ยง 501(c)(3) against the US Catholic Church's anti-abortion political activities; Benten v Kessler, relating to Lader's importation of RU-486 into the US to challenge the Federal government's refusal to approve the drug; and a smaller amount on the ARM v Regan case, which concerns abortion rights and the Constitutional separation of church and state.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Abortion -- Law and legislation-United States -- History -- Sources; Abortion -- Religious aspects -- Catholic Church; Birth control -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources; Birth control -- Religious aspects -- Catholic Church -- History -- Sources; Boston (Mass.) -- History -- Sources; Pro-choice movement -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Reproductive rights -- United States -- History -- Sources; Abolitionists -- Massachusetts -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Abortion -- Social aspects -- United States; Mifepristone -- United States; RU 486; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Abortion Rights Mobilization (Organization); NARAL; Rose, Florence, 1903-1969; Advertisements; articles; Audiotapes; Biographical notes; Books; correspondence; Court cases; Fund raising; Galley proofs; Interviews; Juvenilia; lecture notes; Legal documents; Manuscripts; Publicity; Radio scripts; reports; Research; Reviews; scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Speeches; Videotapes; Writings; Lader, Joan Summers; Lader, Lawrence; Beil, Marshall; Lader, Joan Summers; Beil, Marshall
- Lawrence Lader papers, 1929-2005; 2012-S-0071; 8.5 linear feet (9 boxes and one oversize folder)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Per the deed of gift, this accession of materials is closed until processed. Please contact specialcollections@smith.edu to request expedited processing and access.
  Other Finding Aids
  An unpublished list of the contents of this series can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the first accession of materials donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Lawrence Lader's widow, Joan Lader in 2012.
- Lawrence Lader papers regarding Baker v. Abortion Rights Mobilization (ARM) and Benton v. Kessler, 1977-1992; 2018-S-0006; Beil, Marshall; 4 linear feet (3 record cartons, one full legal document box)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  These materials were collected by Lader before his death, and were subsequently reviewed by legal colleague Marshall Beil (at the request of Lader's widow) to verify that they are appropriate for general research. They were then donated to the Sophia Smith Collection.
  This accession consists of records held by Marshall Beil relating to two lawsuits in which Beil represented Lawrence Lader and/or Abortion Rights Mobilization (ARM):
  Baker v Abortion Rights Mobilization, relating to the enforcement of the anti-electioneering provisions of IRS Code ยง 501(c)(3) against the US Catholic Church's anti-abortion political activities, and
  Benten v Kessler, relating to Larry's importation of RU-486 into the US to challenge the Federal government's refusal to approve the drug.
  It also includes less extensive papers on the ARM v Regan case, which concerns abortion rights and the Constitutional separation of church and state.
  Beil, Marshall
  - Catholic Church and clergy case research, 1978-1987 (Box 1)
    Includes information on Catholic clergy members, church structure, relevant papers on various specific churches and church organizations (Long Island Catholic, the Mormon church, San Diego churches, and Right to Life Committees).
  - Constance Cook working cards for case research, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    Correspondence and research notes of Constance Cook, an attorney from Ithaca, New York.
  - Idaho v. Freeman & NOW case research, 1980 (Box 1)
    The NOW motion to disqualify Idaho's suit and relevant papers.
  - ARM v. Baker discovery documents, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
    Files on the discovery of facets of the United States Catholic Church, the defendants, disposition notices and subpeonas, and related notes and correspondence.
  - ARM v. Baker state and national non-violations, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
    Research and papers on state and national non-violations, plus potential evidence
  - ARM v. Baker official court documents, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    Court booklets, answers to interrogatory, document requests, and documents produced by ARM, Long Island NOW, and the National Women's Health Network.
  - ARM v. Baker notes and various papers, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
    Information, research, court documents, and press relevant to the ARM v. Baker case.
  - ARM v. Baker court files, 1986; 1 linear feet (Box 3, Box 4)
    Includes amicus briefs, briefs for parties involved, appeals, joint appendices, and record roll papers 57-128.
- Additional Lawrence Lader papers regarding Abortion Rights Mobilization (ARM), 1994-2000; 2018-S-0013; .5 linear feet (1 legal document box)
  This series consists of correspondence between Marshall Beil and Lawrence Lader, papers on Benten v. Kessler and other abortion-related court cases, ARM press releases and newsletters, and related publications.
  The materials in this series were sent to the Sophia Smith Collection by Marshall Beil, who had reviewed them at the request of Lawrence Lader's widow.
  - Correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
    Correspondence between Lader and Beil, Beil and clients, and various organizations and people related to court cases under ARM's purview.
  - Court files, Benten v. Kessler and miscellaneous, 1991-2000 (Box 1)
    Court files on the Benten v. Kessler case and other abortion-related court cases represented by Beil.
  - ARM publications and press, 1995-1999 (Box 1)
    ARM publications (newsletters, press releases, bulletins) and related press (newspapers, magazines).